<div xml:id="cdifbase"><head>Basic structure</head> 

<p>The original British National Corpus was provided as an
application of ISO 8879, the Standard Generalized Mark-Up Language
(SGML). This international standard provides, amongst other things, a
method of specifying an application-independent document grammar, in
terms of the elements which may appear in a document, their
attributes, and the ways in which they may legally be combined.  SGML
was a predecessor of XML, the extensible markup language defined by
the World Wide Web Consortium and now in general use on the World Wide
Web. XML was originally designed as a means of distributing SGML
documents on the web.
</p>

<p>This XML edition of the BNC is delivered in an XML format which is
documented in this manual in section <ptr target="#cdifsgml"/> below;
more detailed information about XML itself is readily available in
many places.<note place="foot">The article in Wikipedia (<ptr
target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XML"/>) is probably as
good a starting point as any; another is at <ptr
target="http://homepages.inf.ed.ac.uk/wadler/xml/"/></note>

</p>

<p>The original BNC encoding format was also strongly influenced by the
proposals of the Text Encoding Initiative (<abbr>TEI</abbr>). This
international research project resulted in the development of a set of
comprehensive guidelines for the encoding and interchange of a wide
range of electronic texts amongst researchers. An initial report
appeared in 1991, and a substantially revised and expanded version in
early 1994. A conscious attempt was made to conform to
<abbr>TEI</abbr> recommendations, where these had already been
formulated, but in the first version of the BNC there were a number of
differences in tag names, and models. In the second edition of the BNC
(BNC World), the tagging scheme was changed to conform as far as
possible with the published <title>Recommendations</title> of the TEI
(<ptr target="#TEI94"/>). In the XML edition, this process has continued,
and the corpus schema is now supplied in the form of  a TEI customization: see
further <ptr target="#bnctags"/>.
</p>

<div xml:id="cdifsgml" ><head>Markup conventions</head> 

<p>The BNC XML edition is marked up in XML and encoded in
Unicode. These formats are now so pervasive as to need little
explication here; for the sake of completeness however, we give a
brief summary of their chief characteristics. We strongly recommend
the use of XML-aware processing tools to process the corpus; see
further <ptr target="#cdifsmop"/>. </p>
<p>An XML document, such as the BNC consists of a single <term>root
element</term>, within which are nested occurrences of other element
types. All element occurrences are delimited by
<term>tags</term>. There are two forms of tag, a
<term>start-tag</term>, marking the beginning of an
<term>element</term>, and an <term>end-tag</term> marking its end (in
the case of <soCalled>empty elements</soCalled>, the two may be
combined; see below).
Tags are delimited by the characters &lt; and &gt;, and contain the
name of the element (its <term>gi</term>, for <term>generic
identifier</term>), preceded by a solidus (/) in the case of an
end-tag.
</p>
<p>For example, a heading or title in a written text will be preceded
by a tag of the form <gi>head</gi> and followed by a tag in the form
<gi>/head</gi>. Everything between these two tags is regarded as the
<term>content</term> of an <term>element</term> of type <gi>head</gi>.
</p>
<p><term>Attributes</term> applicable to element instances, if
present, are also indicated within the start-tag, and take the form of
an attribute name, an equals sign and the attribute value, in the form
of a quoted literal. Attribute values are used
for a variety of purposes, notably to represent the part of speech codes
allocated to particular words by the CLAWS tagging scheme. 
</p>
<p>For example, the <gi>head</gi> element may take an attribute
<att>type</att> which categorizes it in some way. A main heading
will thus appear with a start tag <gi>head type="MAIN"</gi>, and a
subheading with a start tag <gi>head type="SUB"</gi>. 
</p>

<p>The names of elements and attributes are case-significant, as are
attribute values. The style adopted throughout the BNC scheme is to
use lower-case letters for identifiers, unless they are derived from
more than one word, in which case the first letter of the second and
any subsequent word is capitalized: examples include
<gi>teiHeader</gi> or <gi>particDesc</gi> (for <q>participant description</q>). </p>

<p>Unless it is empty, every occurrence of an element
must have both a start-tag and an end-tag. Empty elements may use a
special syntax in which start and end-tags are combined together: for
example, the point at which a page break occurs in an original source
is marked <gi>pb/</gi> rather than <gi>pb>&lt;/pb</gi></p>

<p>The BNC  is delivered in UTF-8 encoding: this means that almost
all characters in the corpus are represented directly by the
appropriate Unicode character. The chief exceptions are the ampersand
(&amp;) which is always represented by the special string
<code>&amp;amp;</code>, the double quotation mark, which is sometimes
represented by the special string <code>&amp;quot;</code>, and the
arithmetic less-than sign, which always appears as
<code>&amp;lt;</code>. These <soCalled>named entity
references</soCalled> use a syntactic convention of XML which is
followed by this version of the corpus. All other characters,
including accented letters such as é or special characters such as —,
are represented directly.
</p>

<p>The number of linebreaks in the corpus has been reduced to a
minimum in order to simplify processing by non-XML aware utilities. In particular:
<list>
<item>XML tags are never broken across linebreaks; </item>
<item>the TEI Header prefixed to each text contains no
linebreaks</item>
<item>each <gi>s</gi> element begins on a new line</item>
</list>. Many XML aware utilities are available to convert this representation as required.</p>

 </div>

<div xml:id="xml-eg"><head>An example</head>
<p>Here is the opening of text J10 (a novel by Michael Pearce). In
this example, as elsewhere, we have placed each element on a separate
line for clarity; this is not a requirement of XML however.
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><wtext  type="FICTION"><pb n="5"/>
<div level="1">
  <head>
    <s n="1">
       <w c5="NN1" hw="chapter" pos="SUBST">CHAPTER </w>
       <w c5="CRD" hw="1" pos="ADJ">1</w>
    </s>
  </head>
  <p>
    <s n="2">
       <c c5="PUQ">‘</c>
       <w c5="CJC" hw="but" pos="CONJ">But</w>
       <c c5="PUN">,</c>
       <c c5="PUQ">’ </c>
       <w c5="VVD" hw="say" pos="VERB">said </w>
       <w c5="NP0" hw="owen" pos="SUBST">Owen</w>
       <c c5="PUN">,</c><c c5="PUQ">‘</c>
       <w c5="AVQ" hw="where" pos="ADV">where </w>
       <w c5="VBZ" hw="be" pos="VERB">is </w>
       <w c5="AT0" hw="the" pos="ART">the </w>
       <w c5="NN1" hw="body" pos="SUBST">body</w>
       <c c5="PUN">?</c>
       <c c5="PUQ">’</c>
    </s>
  </p>
    ....
 </div>
</wtext></egXML>
This example has been reformatted to make its structure more apparent:
as noted above, in the actual corpus texts, newlines appear only at
the start of each <gi>s</gi> element, rather than (as here) at the
start of each element. The original files also lack the extra white
space at the start of each line, used in the above example to indicate
how the XML elements nest within one another.</p>

<p>The example begins with the start tag for a <gi>wtext</gi>
(written text) element,
which bears a <att>type</att> attribute, the value of which is
<code>FICTION</code>, the code used for texts derived from published
fiction. The start tag is followed by an empty <gi>pb</gi> element,
which provides the page number in the original source text. This in
turn is followed by the start of a <gi>div</gi> element, which
contains the first subdivision (chapter) of this text. This first
chapter begins with a heading (marked by a <gi>head</gi> element)
followed by a paragraph (marked by the <gi>p</gi> element). Further
details and examples are provided for all of these elements and their
functions elsewhere in this documentation. </p>

<p>Each distinct word and punctuation mark in the text, as identified
by the CLAWS tagger, has been separately tagged with a <gi>w</gi> or
<gi>c</gi> element as appropriate. These elements both bear a
<att>c5</att> attribute, which indicates the code from the CLAWS
C5 tagset allocated to that word by the CLAWS POS-tagger; <gi>w</gi>
elements also bear a <att>pos</att> attribute, which provides a less
fine-grained part of speech classification for the word, and an
<att>hw</att> attribute, which indicates the root form of the
word. For example, the word <q>said</q> in this example has the CLAWS
5 code <val>VVD</val>, the simplified POS tag <val>VERB</val>, and the
headword <val>say</val>.  The sequence of words and punctuation marks
making up a complete segment is tagged as an <gi>s</gi> element, and
bears an <att>n</att> attribute, which supplies its sequence
number within the text. A combination of text identifier (the three
letter code) and <gi>s</gi> number may be used to reference any part
of the corpus: the example above contains J10 1 and J10 2. </p>

<p>This is not, of course, a complete text: in particular, it lacks
the TEI header which is prefixed to each text file making up the
corpus. Its purpose is to indicate how the corpus is encoded. Any XML
aware processing software, including common Web browsers, should be
able to operate directly on BNC texts in XML format. </p>
<p>The remainder of this manual describes in more detail the intended
semantics for each of the XML elements used in the corpus, with
examples of their use. 
</p></div>

<div xml:id="cdif2"><head>Corpus and text elements</head> 
<p>The BNC  contains a large number of
<term>text samples</term>, some spoken and some written. Each such
sample has some associated descriptive or bibliographic information
particular to it, and there is also a large body of descriptive
information which applies to the whole corpus.
</p>

<p>In XML terms, the corpus  consists of a single 
element, tagged <gi>bnc</gi>.  This element contains a single
<gi>teiHeader</gi> element, containing metadata which relates to the
whole corpus, followed by a sequence of <gi>bncDoc</gi>
elements. Each such <gi>bncDoc</gi> element contains its own
<gi>teiHeader</gi>, containing metadata relating to that specific
text, followed by either a <gi>wtext</gi> element (for
written texts) or an <gi>stext</gi> element (for spoken texts). </p>

<p>Each bncDoc element also carries an <att>xml:id</att> attribute, which
supplies its standard three-character identifier.

<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><bncDoc xml:id="ABC">
<teiHeader>
  <!-- header for document ABC here -->
</teiHeader>
<wtext type="FICTION">
  <!-- sentences from ABC (a written text classified as fiction) here -->
</wtext>
</bncDoc>
</egXML>
</p>
<p>The components of the TEI header are fully documented in section <ptr
target="#cdifhd"/>. <!-- Further discussion of XML concepts and practices
is provided in section <ptr target="#cdifsmop"/>.-->
</p>

<p>Note that different elements are used for spoken and written texts
because each has a different substructure; this represents a departure
from <abbr>TEI</abbr> recommended practice.   
</p>
<p>The function of these elements and their attributes may be summarized as follows:
<specList><specDesc key="wtext" atts="type"/><specDesc
key="stext" atts="type"/></specList>
 </p></div> 

<div xml:id="cdifcomp"><head>Segments and words</head> 

<p>The <gi>s</gi> element is the basic organizational principle for
the whole corpus: every text, spoken or written, is represented as a
sequence of <gi>s</gi> elements, possibly grouped into
higher-level constructs, such as paragraphs or utterances. Each
<gi>s</gi> element in turn contains <gi>w</gi> or <gi>c</gi> elements
representing words and punctuation marks.</p>

<p>The <att>n</att> attribute is used to provide a sequential
number for the <gi>s</gi> element to which it is attached. To identify any part of the corpus
uniquely therefore, all that is needed is the three character text
identifier (given as the value of the attribute <att>xml:id</att>
on the <gi>bncDoc</gi> containing the text, followed by the value of
the <att>n</att> attribute of the <gi>s</gi> element containing
the passage to be identified.</p>

<p>These numbers are, as far as possible, preserved across versions of
the corpus, to facilitate referencing. This implies that the sequence
numbering may have gaps, where duplicate sequences or segmentation
errors have been identified and removed from the corpus. In a few
(about 700) cases, sequences formerly regarded as a single <gi>s</gi>
have subsequently been split into two or more <gi>s</gi> units. For
compatibility with previous versions of the corpus, the same number is
retained for each new <gi>s</gi>, but it is suffixed by a fragment
number. For example, in text A18, the <gi>s</gi> formerly numbered
1307, has now been replaced by two <gi>s</gi> elements, numbered
1307_1 and 1307_2 respectively. </p>

<p> Fragmentary sentences such as headings or labels in lists are
also encoded as <gi>s</gi> elements, as in the following example from
text CBE:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><div type="u">
<head type="MAIN">
  <s n="835">
   <w c5="AJ0" hw="serious" pos="ADJ">Serious </w>
   <w c5="NN1" hw="fit" pos="SUBST">fit </w>
   <w c5="PRF" hw="of" pos="PREP">of </w>
   <w c5="NN2" hw="giggle" pos="SUBST">giggles</w>
  </s>
</head>
<p>
<s n="836">
   <w c5="AT0" hw="a" pos="ART">A </w>
   <w c5="NN0" hw="pair" pos="SUBST">PAIR </w>
   <w c5="PRF" hw="of" pos="PREP">of </w>
   <w c5="NN1" hw="tv" pos="SUBST">TV </w>
   <w c5="NN2" hw="newsreader" pos="SUBST">newsreaders </w>
... 
</s>...</p> ... </div></egXML> 
</p>
<p>As noted above, at the lowest level, the corpus consists of
<gi>w</gi> (word) and <gi>c</gi> (punctuation) elements, grouped into
<gi>s</gi> (segment) elements. Each <gi>w</gi> element contains three
attributes to indicate its morphological class or part of speech, as
determined by the CLAWS tagger, a simplified form of that POS code,
and an automatically-derived root form or lemma. Each <gi>c</gi>
element also carries codes for part of speech, but not for lemma. For
example, the word <soCalled>corpora</soCalled> wherever it appears in
the BNC is presented like this: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><w c5="NN2" pos="SUBST"
hw="corpus">corpora </w></egXML></p>

<p>Any white space following a word in the original source is
preserved within the <gi>w</gi> tag, as in the previous example. White
space is not added if no space is present in the source, as in the
following example:

 <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><w c5="NN2" pos="SUBST" hw="corpus">corpora</w><c c5="PUN" pos="PUN">. </c></egXML></p>

 <p>The <gi>w</gi> element encloses a single token as identified by
 the CLAWS tagger. Usually this willl correspond with a word as
 conventionally spelled; there are however two important
 exceptions. Firstly, CLAWS regards certain common abbreviated or
 enclitic forms such as <soCalled>'s</soCalled> in
 <soCalled>he's</soCalled> or <soCalled>dog's</soCalled> as distinct tokens, thus
 enabling it to distinguish them as being an auxiliary verb in the
 first case, and a genitive marker in the second.  For example,
 <soCalled>It's</soCalled> is encoded as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<w c5="PNP" hw="it" pos="PRON">It</w>
<w c5="VBZ" hw="be" pos="VERB">'s </w>
</egXML>while <soCalled>dog's</soCalled> is encoded:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><w c5="NN1" hw="dog" pos="SUBST">dog</w>
<w c5="POS" hw="'s" pos="UNK">'s </w> </egXML></p>
<p> Secondly, CLAWS treats certain common multi-word units as if they
were single tokens, giving the whole of a sequence such as
<soCalled>in spite of</soCalled> a single POS code. These multiword
sequences were not distinguished from individual <gi>w</gi> elements
in earlier versions of the corpus; in the present version however a
new element <gi>mw</gi> (for multiword) has been introduced to mark
them explicitly. The individual components of a <gi>mw</gi> sequence
are also tagged as <gi>w</gi> elements in the same way as
elsewhere. Thus, the phrase <soCalled>in terms of</soCalled>, which
in earlier editions of the BNC would have been encoded as a single
<gi>w</gi> element, is now encoded as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><mw c5="PRP">
 <w c5="PRP" hw="in" pos="PREP">in </w>
 <w c5="NN2" hw="term" pos="SUBST">terms </w>
 <w c5="PRF" hw="of" pos="PREP">of
</w></mw></egXML>
</p>

<p>Detailed information about the procedures by which the part of
speech and lemmatization information was added to the corpus is
provided in section <ptr target="#posguide"/>, which is derived from 
the <title>Manual to accompany The British National Corpus
(Version 2) with Improved Word-class Tagging</title> by Geoffrey Leech
and Nicholas Smith, as distributed along with the BNC World
edition of the corpus. 
A brief summary of the codes used and their significance is also
provided in the reference section below
(<ptr target="#bnctags"/>).

<specList>
<specDesc key="s" atts="n"/>
<specDesc key="w" atts="pos c5 hw"/>
<specDesc key="c" atts="pos c5"/>
<specDesc key="mw" atts="c5"/>
</specList>
</p>
</div>

<div xml:id="cdifed"><head>Editorial indications</head> 
<p>Despite the best efforts of its creators, any corpus as large as
the BNC will inevitably contain many errors, both in transcription and
encoding.  Every attempt has been made to reduce the incidence of such
errors to an acceptable level, using a number of automatic and
semi-automatic validation and correction procedures, but exhaustive
proof-reading of a corpus of this size remains economically
infeasible. Editorial interventions in the marked up texts take three forms. On a
few occasions, where markup or commentary introduced by transcribers
during the process of creating the corpus may be helpful to subsequent
users, it has been retained in the form of an XML comment. On some
occasions, encoders have decided to correct material evidently wrong
in their copy text: such corrections are marked using the
<gi>corr</gi> element. And on several occasions, sampling,
anonymization or other concerns, have led to the omission of
significant parts of the original source; such omissions are marked by
means of the <gi>gap</gi> element. </p>

<p>The transcription and editorial policies defined for the corpus may
not have been applied uniformly by different transcribers and
consequently the usage of these elements is not consistent across all
texts. The <gi>tagsDecl</gi> element in each text's header may be
consulted for an indication of the usage of these and other elements
within it (see further section <ptr target="#hdenc"/>). Their absence
should not be taken to imply that the text is either complete or
perfectly transcribed.
</p>


<p>In the following example, the first three chapters have been omitted
for sampling reasons:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><wtext  type="FICTION">
<div level="1" n="1">
<head>
  <s n="1">
    <w c5="NP0" hw="friday" pos="SUBST">Friday </w>
    <w c5="CRD" hw="16" pos="ADJ">16 </w>
    <w c5="NP0" hw="september" pos="SUBST">September </w>
    <w c5="PRP" hw="to" pos="PREP">to </w>
    <w c5="NP0" hw="tuesday" pos="SUBST">Tuesday </w>
    <w c5="CRD" hw="20" pos="ADJ">20 </w>
    <w c5="NP0" hw="september" pos="SUBST">September</w>
  </s>
</head>
<gap desc="chapters 1–3 of book 1" reason="sampling strategy"/>
<pb n="17"/>
<div level="2" n="4">
<p>
  <s n="2">
    <w c5="AV0" hw="once" pos="ADV">Once </w>
    <w c5="AJ0" hw="free" pos="ADJ">free </w>
    <w c5="PRF" hw="of" pos="PREP">of </w>
    <w c5="AT0" hw="the" pos="ART">the </w>
    <w c5="AJ0" hw="knotted" pos="ADJ">knotted </w>
    <w c5="NN2" hw="tentacle" pos="SUBST">tentacles </w><w c5="PRF"
    hw="of" pos="PREP">of </w><w c5="AT0" hw="the" pos="ART">the
</w><w c5="AJ0" hw="eastern" pos="ADJ">eastern </w><w c5="NN2"
hw="suburb" pos="SUBST">suburbs</w><c c5="PUN">, </c><w c5="NP0"
hw="dalgliesh" pos="SUBST">Dalgliesh </w><w c5="VVD" hw="make"
pos="VERB">made </w><w c5="AJ0" hw="good" pos="ADJ">good </w><w
c5="NN1" hw="time" pos="SUBST">time </w><w c5="CJC" hw="and"
pos="CONJ">and </w><w c5="PRP" hw="by" pos="PREP">by </w><w c5="CRD"
hw="three" pos="ADJ">three </w><w c5="PNP" hw="he" pos="PRON">he
</w><w c5="VBD" hw="be" pos="VERB">was </w><w c5="VVG" hw="drive"
pos="VERB">driving </w><w c5="PRP" hw="through" pos="PREP">through
</w><w c5="NP0" hw="lydsett" pos="SUBST">Lydsett </w><w c5="NN1"
hw="village" pos="SUBST">village</w><c c5="PUN">.</c></s></p>... </div>...</div></wtext><!-- C8T --></egXML> 
</p>
<p>In the following example, a proper name has been omitted: 
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><s n="547">
  <w c5="PNP" hw="i" pos="PRON">I </w>
  <w c5="VVD" hw="ask" pos="VERB">asked </w>
  <w c5="NP0" hw="mr" pos="SUBST">Mr  </w>
  <gap desc="name" reason="anonymization"/>
  <w c5="CJC" hw="and" pos="CONJ">and   </w>
...</s><!-- KBC --></egXML> 
</p>
<p>In the following example, a telephone number has been omitted:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><s n="762"><w c5="PNP" hw="he" pos="PRON">He </w><w c5="VVD" hw="appeal" pos="VERB">appealed </w><w c5="PRP" hw="for" pos="PREP">for </w><w c5="PNI" hw="anyone" pos="PRON">anyone </w><w c5="PRP" hw="with" pos="PREP">with </w><w c5="NN1" hw="information" pos="SUBST">information </w><w c5="TO0" hw="to" pos="PREP">to </w><w c5="VVI" hw="contact" pos="VERB">contact </w><w c5="PNP" hw="he" pos="PRON">him </w><w c5="AVP" hw="on" pos="ADV">on </w><gap desc="telephone number"/><c c5="PUN">.</c></s><!-- K3C --></egXML>
</p>
<p>In the following example, a typographic error in the original has been
corrected:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><s n="48">...
<w c5="AJ0" hw="good" pos="ADJ">good </w>
<w c5="CJC" hw="or" pos="CONJ">or </w>
<corr sic="herioc"> 
   <w c5="AJ0" hw="heroic" pos="ADJ">heroic </w>
</corr>
<w c5="NN1" hw="behaviour" pos="SUBST">behaviour</w>
...</s><!-- B17 --></egXML> 
</p>
<p>In the following example, a word ommitted in the original has been
supplied as correction:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><s n="1838"><mw
								c5="PRP"><w c5="AV0" hw="apart" pos="ADV">Apart </w><w c5="PRP" hw="from" pos="PREP">from </w></mw><w c5="DT0" hw="some" pos="ADJ">some </w><w c5="NN1" hw="eye-liner" pos="SUBST">eye-liner </w><w c5="NN2" hw="aberration" pos="SUBST">aberrations </w><w c5="PRP" hw="as" pos="PREP">as </w><w c5="AT0" hw="a" pos="ART">a </w><w c5="NN1" hw="teenager" pos="SUBST">teenager</w><c c5="PUN">, </c><w c5="NP0" hw="mr" pos="SUBST">Mr </w><w c5="NP0" hw="punch" pos="SUBST">Punch</w><c c5="PUN">, </c><w c5="PNP" hw="it" pos="PRON">it </w><w c5="VM0" hw="must" pos="VERB">must </w><corr sic=""> <w c5="VBI" hw="be" pos="VERB">be </w></corr><w c5="VVN" hw="say" pos="VERB">said</w><c c5="PUN">, </c><w c5="VBZ" hw="be" pos="VERB">is </w><w c5="AV0" hw="absolutely" pos="ADV">absolutely </w><w c5="AJ0" hw="straight" pos="ADJ">straight </w><w c5="PRP-CJS" hw="as" pos="PREP">as </w><w c5="AT0" hw="a" pos="ART">a </w><w c5="NN1-VVB" hw="die" pos="SUBST">die</w><c c5="PUN">.</c></s><!-- BNT --></egXML> 
</p>


<p>The usage of these elements may be summarized as follows:

<specList>
<specDesc key="gap" atts="desc reason resp"/>
<specDesc key="corr" atts="sic rend resp"/>
</specList>

<!-- why doesnt corr get resp from the same class as gap? -->

Note that the <gi>sic</gi> element used in preceding editions of the
BNC is no longer used.</p>
</div>

</div>